<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Path Less Travelled</title><link href="http://example.com/"></link><link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://echaozh.com/feed.xml"></link><updated>2014-02-26T14:10:43.216Z</updated><id>http://echaozh.com/feed.xml</id><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><entry><id>http://echaozh.com/posts/functional_cpp.html</id><link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://echaozh.com/posts/functional_cpp.html"></link><title>Programming in C++ in a More Functional Way</title><published>2013-12-29</published><updated>2013-12-29</updated><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I&#39;m playing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Neverlord/libcppa&quot;&gt;libcppa&lt;/a&gt;, by
implementing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ramcloud.stanford.edu/wiki/download/attachments/11370504/raft.pdf&quot;&gt;Raft consensus protocol&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am writing tests, I become more and more certain that classes is not the
right pieces to make up a program. A class, or its encapsulation by using private
members and methods can make some tests hard or impossible. If you lift the
members to public, then the class is not necessary any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raft is a consensus protocol, meaning it can make different nodes across the
network to agree with things. Any participant has to be in 1 of 3 modes: the
follower, the candidate, and the leader. Only the leader answers to requests
from clients. All the others are followers, and they only observe and acknowledge
to logs from the leader generated after accepting write requests. They don&#39;t talk
to the clients, not even read requests. Which means, there is no way to tell if
the internal states of the follower is correct, as there is no such interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test the follower behavior, I either have to peek at its state after each
transaction, or execute another transaction to see if the second one works and
guess that the state must be correct. Well, why bother, so I take the first
approach. But how can I access the state if it&#39;s a private member of the
&lt;code&gt;raft&lt;/code&gt; class? Then there&#39;s another choice to make:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the test suite a friend of the class;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the state field public, or make a public accessor;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make the state field public when it&#39;s testing;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;forget it, don&#39;t define a &lt;code&gt;raft&lt;/code&gt; class in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, since I am writing this post, I definately took the last option.
Friends are uglym and I don&#39;t like tests forcing things into the tested code.
Also, having different code for tests and production immmediately sounds like a
terrible idea, as the production code is actually not tested. Though, wrong
accessibility of fields should be catchable by the compiler, so it&#39;s not such a
huge problem by itself, but it still smells. Making a public accessor is a bad
idea as nothing besides the tests will require it. Making the state field public
directly breaks encapsulation, and renders the class wrapper unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we have closures, why do we need classes any more? C doesn&#39;t have classes,
but it&#39;s still possible to achieve polymorphism in C, via function pointers. And
closures are the upgraded version of function pointers, with states to get rid of
the horrible &lt;code&gt;void* arg&lt;/code&gt; every time we define a callback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve read somewhere another day, that Haskell, with closures, doens&#39;t need
classes in the OO sense. The argument is that, (in principle, as I cannot find
the link now), classes is basically a way to bind states to functions; since
closure is another way to do it, and more reflexible, there is no need to define
a class every time we need a small difference in behavior. We can just define a
lambda function, capture whatever state it needs, and pass it on. It cannot be
more insightful. Think of the anonymous classes in Java. And think of factory
methods. Class names are rarely used, only to instantiate. Later when being used,
the exact class names don&#39;t appear in user code, or polymophism doesn&#39;t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the 3 modes transit to each other within the state machine, the implementation
of each mode should actually be private. To make them testable, I broke the
&lt;code&gt;raft&lt;/code&gt; class into 3, 1 for each mode. Also, they&#39;re not classes. They are
each a function returning the behavior for the libcppa actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking down the class actually helps make the code more mock-testable. If I
went with the class, or classes, much of the infrastructure would definately go
into the class/classes. Like log reading/writing, or random timeout generation.
When testing, to have to read/write logs from/to the disk is too inconvenient,
even if you don&#39;t have to initialize the log files beforehand, and remove them
afterwards. It should be made &lt;code&gt;virtual&lt;/code&gt; to be overridden in the derived mock
class. However, it&#39;s more propable that I will go with the real log processing
implementation and test them together. However, the fact that log processing
itself should have its own test set. Indirect tests may not give the most
thourough coverage. Also, it&#39;s highly impossible I would make random timeout
generation &lt;code&gt;virtual&lt;/code&gt;, but being able to change the timeout distribution is
still useful, say to test conflict cases when multiple candidates share similar
election deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closures instead of classes make switching strategies/policies easier. With a
&lt;code&gt;candidate&lt;/code&gt; class, if I want to &lt;code&gt;become&lt;/code&gt; it when the &lt;code&gt;follower&lt;/code&gt; times
out, the &lt;code&gt;follower&lt;/code&gt; behavior must templated to be able to instantiate
different &lt;code&gt;candidate&lt;/code&gt; classes on demand. With closures, the template is
not necessary, and code can be put in source files instead of headers. (Though
it actually is templated now, not for modes, but for mocking log entries.)
Closures also make it possible to write table driven factory methods. You cannot
put classes as values into a map, but you can do it to closures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In C++ 11, free functions &lt;code&gt;begin()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;end()&lt;/code&gt; are added to make ranged
for possible for all iterable things. Not all of them have corresponding methods
in their interface, and can be modified to have them. And overloaded operators
are sometimes outside the type. Free functions can extend types and closures make
them more powerful. I think it&#39;s time to define more functions and fewer classes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://echaozh.com/posts/teasers-and-tags.html</id><link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://echaozh.com/posts/teasers-and-tags.html"></link><title>Adding Teasers and Tags for Posts with Harp</title><published>2013-10-10</published><updated>2013-10-10</updated><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Starting a blog using &lt;a href=&quot;http://harpjs.com&quot;&gt;Harp&lt;/a&gt; is
&lt;a href=&quot;http://harpjs.com/docs/quick-start&quot;&gt;very easy&lt;/a&gt;. Here&#39;s how to add teasers to the
front page, and how to make tag pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Adding Teasers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s add support for WordPress style teasers: teaser and the rest of the content
separated by a &lt;code&gt;&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/code&gt; comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, first you add the comment to your posts, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6916985.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6916985#file-post-example&quot;
     target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    Open the Gist
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in &lt;code&gt;index.jade&lt;/code&gt;, you can render the post and strip away the comment and
everything after it. Then you got your teaser. This is possible because partials
in the Harp flavored &lt;a href=&quot;jade-lang.com&quot;&gt;Jade&lt;/a&gt; is implemented by passing in a
&lt;code&gt;partial()&lt;/code&gt; function which is callable by JavaScript code in the Jade template!
Calling &lt;code&gt;partial(postFilePath)&lt;/code&gt; actually returns the rendered post as a
JavaScript string. Then it&#39;s easy to call &lt;code&gt;String.prototype.replace()&lt;/code&gt; to strip
away everything you don&#39;t need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JavaScript code is really simple (assuming you put your posts under
public/posts):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917018.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917018#file-teaser-extraction-js&quot;
     target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    Open the Gist
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prefix each line with &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; to make it unbuffered code in Jade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The teaser will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917031.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917031#file-teaser-html&quot;
     target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    Open the Gist
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put it in the front page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Making Tag Pages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, more precisely, making a tag page to dynamically list posts for different
tags. Harp, AFAIK, doesn&#39;t allow you to create pages without a template. And it&#39;s
for developing WebApps. So the solution is obvious: you need client side
JavaScript to make it possible (unless you create a page template for each tag
by hand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solution is to populate the tag page with all tags, and hide those tags you
don&#39;t want. The wanted tag name is passed in via the hash part in the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tags, as I mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/to-harp.html&quot;&gt;Migrated Blog to Harp&lt;/a&gt; post,
should be specified in the &lt;code&gt;_data.json&lt;/code&gt; file. Extracting tags from the file is
really straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source of my tag template:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917115.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917115#file-tag-page-jade&quot;
     target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    Open the Gist
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Jade Snippet to Find Page Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harp only sends in a &lt;code&gt;current&lt;/code&gt; object with path info of the template. To find
data registered for the specific template, use the JavaScript snippet below (and
don&#39;t forget to prefix the lines):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917128.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/echaozh/6917128#file-page-data-js&quot;
     target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
    Open the Gist
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put it in &lt;code&gt;_page.jade&lt;/code&gt; and include it in almost every Jade template.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://echaozh.com/posts/to-harp.html</id><link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://echaozh.com/posts/to-harp.html"></link><title>Migrated Blog to Harp</title><published>2013-10-08</published><updated>2013-10-08</updated><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have migrated my blog to &lt;a href=&quot;http://harpjs.com&quot;&gt;Harp&lt;/a&gt;! Now I&#39;ve waved goodbye to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jaspervdj.be/blaze/&quot;&gt;Blaze HTML&lt;/a&gt;,
and am using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jade-lang.com&quot;&gt;Jade&lt;/a&gt; instead. I am pretty happy with the
migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I am not using Harp as a server, I&#39;m happy with its compilation process.
With native Jade support, I can finally get rid of my Makefiles! Jade also
supports embedded JavaScript logic, so tag pages can be generated directly in the
Jade template, rather than in a Jekyll plugin, which is definately more
convenient in my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the meta data is put in a separate &lt;code&gt;_data.json&lt;/code&gt; file
in each directory, rather than scattering in each page. This is arguably better
than in-page meta data, as it allows easy tag extraction. And it makes each page
clean, as the meta data is not always syntactically correct, which sometimes
makes me, a purist, itch somewhere unscratchable. And it eases meta data
processing logic in the static site generator. Though, sometimes it is more
annoying to open up another file to write meta data to, and you tend to forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole, I am pretty happy with the transition. Oh, I had to patch the
Terraform library depended by Harp to make nested layout templates possible. I
will send the patch upstream some time later. Can&#39;t believe they left such useful
functionality out.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://echaozh.com/posts/luapp.html</id><link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://echaozh.com/posts/luapp.html"></link><title>LuaPP, a Wrapper for Lua in C++</title><published>2013-10-07</published><updated>2013-10-07</updated><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/echaozh/luapp&quot;&gt;LuaPP&lt;/a&gt; is a library I wrote to ease the embedding of Lua scripts into C++ applications. It&#39;s more C++-ish, and much easier to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The library makes Lua tables, functions, and other primitive types directly accessible from the C++ code. Instead of manipulating the stack, you can directly get and set values to a global variable, or access fields of a table, or invoke a function as if it was native. You can pass in arguments of the std::string type, and it will be converted. You can even pass in Lua tables as arguments. Variadic arguments are used in the function interface to make invocations look and feel more native.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you embed Lua into your application, you normally want to load external Lua scripts, execute them, and interact with them (say invoke functions defined in the scripts). LuaPP helps you interact with the scripts easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote another library &lt;em&gt;taveren&lt;/em&gt; using LuaPP to embed Lua scripts into strings. It makes expansions in string literals like in Bash or Ruby possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://echaozh.com/posts/python-dbtxn.html</id><link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://echaozh.com/posts/python-dbtxn.html"></link><title>Introducing Python dbtxn Library</title><published>2013-10-06</published><updated>2013-10-06</updated><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/echaozh/python-dbtxn&quot;&gt;python-dbtxn&lt;/a&gt; is a library I wrote to ease db accessing from Python programs. Directly calling Python DBI leaves a lot of boilerplate code all over the place, and boilerplate code is bad. I googled, and there are no dbtxn like libraries, so I wrote my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 sources of boilerplate code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cursor.execute() and cursor.fetchall()/cursor.rowcount/cursor.lastrowid have to be separately called to execute a SQL and then acquire the results/information of the execution;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;connection/cursor objects have to be acquired first, and then closed. The transaction has to be committed or aborted each time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first problem can be easily fixed by wrapping your own function around the execute() and fetchall() calls. At the lowest level, the DBI doesn&#39;t want to incur the cost of info fetching on those callers who don&#39;t care about the info. This is easily understandable by one from the C++ background (ie, me). However, it&#39;s unwieldy, and at a higher level, I can make my own decision to pay the price each time I execute a SQL statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second source of boilerplate code comes from the execution model of the Python DBI. The DBI is an API to be called, rather than a framework to make the calls. When there is no transaction to commit, the passive API/library model works fine and unobtrusive. However, so long as transactions are involved, boilerplate code emerges as all transactions are alike. The dbtxn library manages the transaction, setting up the necessary exception-safe resource releasing mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dbtxn library does more than simply managing transactions. Actually, it separates the business logic which doesn&#39;t care about the underlying database from the callers who know and play with the dirty details. The business logic only needs to know about the SQLs and the processing of the result set, but not the connection, cursor or transaction involved. And business logic should be composable into bigger transactions, without having to pass cursors around. This is all possible with dbtxn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generators instead of plain functions are chosen as the interface of the library. This is straightforward, as the callee of the dbtxn() function &lt;em&gt;generates&lt;/em&gt; SQLs to be executed by dbtxn(), which forms an obvious producer/consumer relationship. You can yield multiple SQLs from the same generator without returning to dbtxn(), and without dbtxn() passing in anything when calling the logic, polluting its interface. dbtxn() also handles nested generators, making the SQL generators composable. SQLs in the same transaction can be grouped into multiple generators, making the code more maintainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using generators makes mocking the database for the business logic a breeze. You don&#39;t need a database or mocking the DBI. You don&#39;t even need the dbtxn library. To test the logic, you just need to call it and send() in data as the result set. Also, the send() calls and the _yield_s can be easily paired, without any bookkeeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;code&gt;@in_txn&lt;/code&gt; decorator is provided to remove the cluttering calls of dbtxn(). Decorated by it, the generators can be called as if they&#39;re ordinary functions. &lt;code&gt;@for_recurse&lt;/code&gt; is provided to make nested generator look like ordinary functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, dbtxn() looks a lot like a monad, namely, the STM monad. The goal to encapsulate computation is close, but the implementation is not. I will work to make it more monadic.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><id>http://echaozh.com/posts/first-post.html</id><link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://echaozh.com/posts/first-post.html"></link><title>My First Blog Post Here</title><published>2013-09-28</published><updated>2013-09-28</updated><author><name>Zhang Yichao</name><email>echaozh#gmail.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my very first blog post on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; powered
static blog site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts are generated from Markdown drafts. Layouts and other HTML files are
generated using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jaspervdj.be/blaze/&quot;&gt;Blaze HTML&lt;/a&gt;. Raw HTML feels ugly,
especially with unbreakable long strings as attribute values. Generating HTMLs
with DSLs solves this problem effectively. I am considering switching to
some Ruby DSL later.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>